<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Steven Brooks' Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://stevenabrooks.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://stevenabrooks.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-17T09:22:16-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://stevenabrooks.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Brooks]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenabrooks.github.io/blog/2013/06/15/testing-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-15T15:31:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenabrooks.github.io/blog/2013/06/15/testing-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was quickly drawn to <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/duien/testing-ruby">&ldquo;Testing Ruby&rdquo;</a>  by Emily Price because as a rookie programmer I have come to realize that things such as planning and testing are very important.</p>

<p><img src="http://stevenabrooks.github.io/images/Screen3.png" alt="Ruby Testing" /></p>

<p>She writes that testing does many things for a programmer including:</p>

<ol>
<li>Ensuring the code is correct</li>
<li>Promoting good practice</li>
<li>Giving reference to how to code actually works.</li>
</ol>


<p>In the first two weeks at Flatiron School, testing out my code before moving on has become very important.  If I can know for certain that a method works (by testing), I never have to worry about that method later on in my program.  It seems like such a simple idea but it was only something I found important after writing dozens of lines of code and realizing one of the first few lines did not work.</p>

<p>One pointer that Price writes about that I learned was to:</p>

<ol>
<li>Write your test first</li>
</ol>


<p>This is something that I can see would be very useful.  At this point in my programming career I am just learning how to do that so this slideshow comes at a good time for me.</p>

<p>Some of the things I thought of during my first two weeks as a programmer that she brought up were:</p>

<ol>
<li>Get instant notification when you have an issue</li>
<li>Write as little code as possible to test</li>
</ol>


<p>As my skills as a programmer grow, I would like to be able to create some sort of a process in which I develop certain ways to test my code to find errors as soon as I can.</p>

<p>Price also has a <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/duien/git-an-introduction">Git Introduction</a> slideshow on <a href="https://speakerdeck.com">speakerdeck</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pretty Juiced About the Work I Did Last Night]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenabrooks.github.io/blog/2013/06/11/post-number-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-11T08:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenabrooks.github.io/blog/2013/06/11/post-number-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This morning will be the seventh day of The Flatiron School.  Yesterday (the sixth day) was by far the most challenging day for me.  Yesterday we were introduced to many new things in the ruby language and it became a lot to comprehend all at once.  As yesterday was seemingly overwhelming, it became very clear to me that no matter what the issue, the process becomes very important.</p>

<p>We were given a homework assignment to create a basketball game with the following guidelines:</p>

<p><img src="http://stevenabrooks.github.io/images/Screen1.png" alt="homework guidelines" /></p>

<p>For my seventh day, this assignment also felt overwhelming.  Luckily for me (some would say), I have an hour long bus commute going home so it was a great opportunity to do some reading on hashes (which is how we were supposed to create this data).</p>

<p>While this feels like a lot of information for me (or at least it did!), remembering the process became key (play on word).  I chose to begin by planning out everything and talking myself through what these hashes would visually look like.  Eventually I was able to visualize these hashes as simple numbered lists:</p>

<p><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-wk8cXlINClk/UTBiAHyIO0I/AAAAAAAAA3g/qu3POwCibd0/s1600/03-Finished+Multilevel+List.png" alt="numbered list" /></p>

<p>Eventually, my code ended up looking something like this (which I&rsquo;m very proud of):</p>

<p><img src="http://stevenabrooks.github.io/images/Screen2.png" alt="my code" /></p>

<p>I am very happy with what I did on this homework assignment as I successfully took a large project and was able to plan out my execution well and break it down into smaller parts.</p>

<p>Later on in the assignment I was asked to make calls to the hash $basketball_game which maybe I&rsquo;ll talk about in another post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blog Post 1.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://stevenabrooks.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-09T17:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://stevenabrooks.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m excited to begin blogging about my experience in learning to become a programmer and especially my experience as a student at The Flatiron School.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to write these posts and have this blog tailored to a wide variety of people ranging from someone who has no programming knowledge to those who are masters in the field (I&rsquo;m sure once my development skills and vocabulary grow a good number of these posts will begin to be more technical.)  I can promise this specific blog will be different than other blogs built by programmers because I believe my background is very unique to this field.  While my fellow classmates come from many different background ranging from professional skydivers to accountants at Goldman Sachs, the only job I&rsquo;ve had has been as a professional baseball player.  One the other side of the coin I cannot promise that I will have perfect grammar or that I will not curse from time to time.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d also like to thank Max Jacobson (a fellow classmate) for helping me in debugging issues to set up this blog to my Github account.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
